Alexander Fred-Ojala

Al, Data Science, Blockchain & Innovation Strategy · Education · Research

1609 La Vereda Rd. Berkeley, CA 94709, USA

□ (+1) 510-993-6337 | ■ afo@berkeley.edu | ★ alex.fo | □ afo | □ alexanderfo



Summary __

AI, Data Science, and Blockchain expert with an entrepreneurial mindset. Research Director and Instructor at UC Berkeley, the #1 Public University in the world. I educate industry leaders around the world on how to make emerging technologies useful and maximizing their utility.

Work Experience __

Sutardja Center for Entrepreneurship & Technology, UC Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA

RESEARCH DIRECTOR, DATA LAB & CO-FOUNDER BLOCKCHAIN LAB

Aug. 2017 - Present

- Research and teaching related to the application of emerging technologies. Manage data and Blockchain related projects in cooperation with industry partners and researchers.
- Project Manager and Lead Data Scientist of the global research project The Berkeley Innovation Index
- Websites: scet.berkeley.edu/data-lab || scet.berkeley.edu/blockchain-lab || berkeleyinnovationindex.org

Industrial Engineering and Operations Research, College of Engineering, UC Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA

LECTURER, CO-CREATOR OF DATA-X, AND VISITING SCHOLAR

Oct 2016 - Present

- Lecturer and co-creator of the UC Berkeley class IEOR135 / IEOR 290 Applied Data Science with Venture Applications
- I have taught 350+ students, and coached 80+ open-ended data science projects.
- Developed course material and co-constructed the teaching framework
- · Developed and have taught a 3day executive education program, based on the class material. Hosted globally.
- Website: data-x.blog

InnoQuant San Francisco, CA, USA

CO-FOUNDER & COO

Feb 2017 - June 2018

 $\bullet \quad \text{Software and data-driven approach to quantify organization's innovation capability. Revenue positive, 10k+ users. www.inno-quant.com} \\$

Auranest Inc. Lund, Sweden

CMO & Founding Team

Jan 2014 - Jan 2016

• Part of the management team and head of the five people marketing team. Raised seed round. www.auranest.com

Wheely's / Studio Total / Nordic Society for Invention and Discovery

Malmö, Sweden

PROJECT MANAGER, FOUNDING TEAM, COPYWRITER

Sep 2013 - Jan 2014

· Launched crowd-funding campaigns that raised \$100k+: Wheely's (accepted into Y Combinator 2015), Wall of Sound etc. wheelys.com

Education

UC Berkeley Berkeley, CA, USA

M.Sc. Mathematical Statistics \parallel GPA: 4.0 / 4.0

Aug 2015 - Oct 2016

- $\bullet \ \ \text{Graduate Studies in the Department of Mathematics / Statistics. Studied Data Science, Applied Mathematics, and Entrepreneurship.}$
- Master Thesis: Construction of the Berkeley Innovation Index A Higher Order Item Response Theory Approach

Lund University Lund, Sweden

M.Sc. Mathematical Statistics and Financial Modeling | GPA: 5.0 / 5.0

Aug 2014 - Sept 2016

- Graduate Student Instructor: Linear Algebra Fall 2014, Spring 2015. Taught classes 2-3 times per week and corrected exams.
- Awarded: LU's Education Abroad stipend, the Anna Whitlock Foundation stipend, Hakon Hansson's stipend, Crafoordska Stiftelsen's stipend.

Lund University & Uppsala University

Lund & Uppsala, Sweden

B.Sc. Engineering Physics | Minor in Macroeconomics || GPA: 4.87 / 5.0

Aug 2009 - May 2013

- Teaching Assistant: Calculus and Linear Algebra 2011-2013. Hosted teaching sessions for 30+ engineering students 2-3 times per week.
- Awarded: The Hilbert Scholarship, Teacher of the Year Award, AF's stipend, Krischansta nation's scholarship, Dagny & Eilert Ekwall's scholarship.

13TH JULY 2018 CV · ALEXANDER FRED-OJALA 1

Program Committees

2018 -	Board Member, Muovitech AB , The Largest manufacturer of Geothermal Products in Europe with over 100	Sweden
	employees in eight countries	
2015	Chairman of the Nominations Committee, Brygghuset FINN, Elected the new Board	Sweden
2014	Industry Mentor, Forsberg's School, Mentored Johan Bylund's examination project.	Sweden

Published Papers & Articles _____

- **1 Fred-Ojala**, **A.**, Sidhu, I., & Charlotta, J. (2018). A quantitative approach to measure, track and forecast innovation capability within individuals and organizations. *ICIMSA Hong Kong*.
- 2 Sidhu, I., Ferry, T., & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2018). Breaking the Zuckerberg myth: Successful entrepreneurs have 10 years of prior employment. *ICE IEEE Stuttgart, Germany*.
- 3 Sidhu, I. & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2018a). Applying entrepreneurial teaching methods to advanced technical STEM courses. *ICE IEEE Stuttgart*, *Germany*.
- 4 Sidhu, I. & **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** (2018b). The future of Blockchain A Berkeley perspective. *SCET, College of Engineering, UC Berkeley*.
- **Fred-Ojala**, **A.** & Eng Larsson, J. (2016). *Construction of the Berkeley Innovation Index: A higher-order item response theory model approach*. Master Thesis.
- 6 Sidhu, I., **Fred-Ojala**, **A.**, & et al. (2016). *Berkeley Innovation Index: An approach for measuring and diagnosing individual's and organizations' innovation capabilities*. Berkeley Electronic Press.

Presentations & Keynotes _____

May 2018 Opening Speaker , TiE Inflect: Blockchain Bootcamp	Santa Clara, USA
May 2018 Keynote Speaker & Mentor, Berkeley Method of Entrepreneurship Bootcamp	HKBU, Hong Kong
Apr 2018 Presenter , UC Berkeley, College of Engineering: Showcase to Donors	Berkeley, USA
Nov 2017 Panelist & Innovation Expert, Tech Match Malaysia	San Mateo, USA
Oct 2017 Keynote , Innovation in Silicon Valley: Delegation Visit from China's National Statistics Bureau	Berkeley, USA

Honors & Awards

2015-2016	UC Berkeley Exchange Scholar, I received the opportunity to complete my Master's degree (tuition free) at	Sweden
2013 2010	UC Berkeley	Sweden
2014	Auranest, 2nd Place, Venture Cup, The World's Largest Business Plan Competition	Sweden
2013	Auranest, Top 50 Most Innovative Startups, ACE Europe	Seoul, S.Korea
2013	Student Teacher of the Year, Lund University	Sweden

Organizer of Masterclasses and Bootcamps _____

2.5 days Bootcamps: Data-X Masterclass in Hong Kong

Hong Kong Productivity Council

CREATOR, PRESENTER

Jan 2018, May 2018

• Organized and taught two bootcamps on AI, Machine Learning, and Blockchain to industry leaders and academics in Hong Kong.

2day Bootcamp: Data-X Masterclass in Prague

xPort / VSE, Prague

CREATOR, PRESENTER

VOLUNTARY WORK

Jan 2018, May 2018

• Organized and taught a 2day bootcamp on AI and Machine Learning to industry leaders and academics in Hong Kong.

Extracurricular Activity _____

Engineers without Borders

Malmö, Sweden

2014 - 2015

• Mathematics Teacher, helping Syrian Refugees with their Homework.

13TH JULY 2018 CV · ALEXANDER FRED-OJALA 2

Head of Department 2010

• Student Board. 200k+ SEK in economic responsibility and head of 40+ voluntary student workers.

Skills____

Programming Python, R, Spark, Java, Javascript, Solidity, Matlab, Bash

Web HTML5, CSS, Flask
Misc SQL, Git, Excel, LTEX

Languages Swedish (native), English (fluent), Spanish (beginner)

Interests Data Science, Mathematics, Entrepreneurship, Yoga, Tennis, Running, Programming, Blockchain, and Writing.